Bowery Gallery
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
1969-2008
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Bowery Gallery
3.1 linear feet
The records of the Bowery Gallery, a non-profit, artist-run, cooperative gallery, measure 3.1 linear feet and date from 1969-2008. Business records, letters, exhibition files, guest registers, printed material and photographs document the gallery's activities and artists.
Provenance
Donated 2003 and 2008 by the Bowery Gallery via Barbara Grossman, and Lynda Caspe, founding members of the Bowery Gallery, and Marylou Schuck. Grossman maintained the Gallery records.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original records requires an appointment. Use of audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Accruals
An additional 0.4 linear feet of Bowery Gallery records dated circa 2002-2008 were accessioned in 2008 and remain unprocessed.
Historical Note
In 1969, eighteen artists founded the Bowery Gallery as a non-profit, artist-run cooperative gallery in New York City. The gallery's original mission was to promote contemporary art and artists during a time when abstract art and pop art dominated. In 1991, Bowery Gallery began sponsoring an annual national competition and juried show for artists working in two-dimensional media.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Bowery Gallery, a non-profit, artist-run cooperative gallery in New York City, measure 3.1 linear feet and date from 1969-2008. Business records, letters, exhibition files, guest registers, printed material and photographs document the gallery's activities and artists.
An additional 0.4 linear feet of Bowery Gallery records dated circa 2002-2008 were accessioned in 2008 and remain unprocessed. This accretion contains minutes and other business records, exhibition schedules, exhibition announcements, and Bowery Artists Tribute, Volume 1 (2008). Also found is a DVD copy of an audiovisual recording of the gallery's inaugural exhibition (October 31, 1969).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series:
Series 1: Business Records, 1969-2002 (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 2: Letters, 1974-1997 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1983-1994 (Box 1; 4 folders)
Series 4: Guest Registers, 1976-2001 (Boxes 1-2; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1969-2001 (Boxes 2-4; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographic Materials, 1997-1999 (Box 3; 0.1 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Topical:
Art galleries, Cooperative--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Video recordings; Visitors' books; Photographs
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Business Records, 1969-2002, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
  Record book contains first treasurer's records and artists' accounts. Incorporation documents include the Gallery's bylaws.
  - Curriculum Vitae of Artists, Armstrong-Virgil, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incorporation of Gallery, 1985-1993, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Lease Information (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Members' Lists, 1970-2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1977-2000, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - Press Releases and Price Lists, 1969, 1983-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Record Book, circa 1969, 1983, undated, (1 volume, removed from binder) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rules and Regulations, Fact Sheet, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letters, 1974-1997, Series 2:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Letters concern Gallery activities and business matters.
  - Letters, 1974-1997, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
- Exhibition Files, 1983-1994, Series 3:; (Box 1; 4 folders)
  Documentation of the "25th Anniversary Exhibition" includes letters and photographs.
  - "Bowery on the Bowery," 1983, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "25th Anniversary Exhibition," 1994, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
- Guest Registers, 1976-20001, Series 4:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.0 linear feet)
  11 volumes record names, addresses, and comments of visitors to the Gallery's exhibitions.
  - Volume 1: 1973-1993, (1 volume) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Volumes 2-10: 1993-2001, (10 volumes) (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
- Printed Material, 1969-2001, Series 5:; (Boxes 2-4; 0.9 linear feet)
  Printed material documents Bowery Gallery's exhibitions and artists.
  - Exhibition Catalogues, 1992, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gallery Announcements, 1971-1992, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 12-25)
  - Gallery Announcements, 1992-2000, undated, (5 folders; oversized material housed in Box 4) (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - National Competition Forms, 1992-2001 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newsletter, "News from Bowery Gallery," 1986-2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1971, 1977-1986, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Poster 1974, (oversized material housed in Box 4) (Box 3)
  - Oversized Printed Material, 1969-1997, undated, (from Box 3, folders 1-5) (Box 4)
- Photographic Materials, 1997-1999 1997-1999, Series 6:; (Box 3; 0.1 linear ft.)
  Photographs and negative record Bowery Gallery exhibition installations, and there are photographs and 35-mm color slides of artwork.
  Additional photographs are found with the exhibition files (Series 3).
  - Installation Views, 1997-1999, (photographs, negatives) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Artwork, undated, (photographs, 35-mm color slides) (Box 3, Folder 10)